XINYUN CHEN: Hold on.
Now, let's get started
for the first lecture
of this class, Advanced
Large Language Model Agents.
I'm Xinyun Chen.
I'm a research scientist
at Google DeepMind,
and I'm instructing this
course with Professor Dawn Song
here at UC Berkeley, and
Kaiyu Yang from Meta.
We also have an amazing TA team
who help us a lot on sorting out
the course logistics.
It was the head here, Alex, and
readers, Tara, Ashwin and Jason.
Last semester we launched the
first version of this LLM agents
course, both here at UC
Berkeley and also on MOOC.
Last semester we had a very
amazing line of guest speakers,
talking about very broad
topics about LLM agents.
So we will discuss about
the fundamental [INAUDIBLE]
reasoning techniques,
the agent workflows
and different
applications, et cetera.
And we had around 15,000
people registered on MOOC.
We also launched a hackathon
which attracted around 3,000
people participated globally.
And we are very grateful for
this generous sponsorship from
our industry partners, who
gave us around $200,000 support
in prices and resources.
We will announce the
hackathon winners very soon.
So stay tuned.
Now, let's go back
to LLM agents.
So the code of a large
language model based agent
is that the brain of this agent
is a large language model, which
is going to perform reasoning
and planning to take action
at each time step.
Then with this action to
interact with the environment,
it will receive the feedback
and revise its internal memory
so that it can better plan
for the next step to take.
So with this [? text ?]
agent framework,
it allows the LLM to also
utilize this external feedback
and tools whenever available,
so that it can further
expand its capability
and to give
to get more informed decision in
its own decision making process.
So some common components
in the agent framework
include tool use and retrieval.
Then why do you want to empower
these large language models
with the agent framework?
Because solving real
world tasks typically
involves a trial
and error process,
especially when we deploy this
LLM agent in a new environment.
It really needs to interact
with the environment
to understand some
success and failure
modes in different actions
so that it is able to revise
its own internal memory.
At the same time,
leveraging external tools
and retrieving from external
knowledge for expanded LLM
capabilities.
And with the more like--
with this agent, your workflow
design becomes more mature.
It also facilitates the
accomplishment of complex tasks.
This includes tasks
decomposition,
allocation of subtasks, division
of labor for collaboration
between different
specialized modules
and multi-agent generation.
Many people are saying
that this year, 2025,
will be the year of agents.
Nowadays, we have already
seen explosion of LLM agents
for various applications.
And in many domains,
actually, these agents
transformed how previous people
are thinking about all these AI
models can-- how these
AI models can behave.
So some very successful
demonstrations
and also practical use cases
include code generation,
computer use, personal
assistant and robotics.
And this list of applications
will keep growing in the future
as well.
And also there are some domains
like education, finance, et
cetera, where we already have
seen an emergence of a pretty
nice LLM-based agents.
Another factor that further
drives this excitement about LLM
agent development is about
this recent rapid progress
of reasoning models, starting
from September last year
with the release of OpenAI o1
And starting from that model,
we have also seen a lot of
great reasoning progress
during the meantime.
For example, last month
we saw the release
of the Gemini 2.0 Flash
Thinking model and also
the OpenAI o3 model.
And this month, we saw the
release of DeepSeek-R1 and Kimi
k1.5.
And also within the
same model series,
we can see a very
drastic improvement
from different
versions of the model.
So, for example, there is a
rapid progress of performance
for OpenAI o1 to o3.
And also if we compare the
current Gemini Thinking model
to our initial version
released last month,
there are also a lot of
improvement we can see.
And if we think about this
progress in reasoning,
the most impressive
performance we have seen so far
are in math and
coding, especially
for solving those very
challenging problems.
For example, last year with the
Alpha Proof and Alpha Geometry
system developed by my
colleagues at Google DeepMind,
they received the silver medal
or nearly gold medal performance
in IMO last year.
And also with the more
recent OpenAI o3 model,
it shows that it can
be ranked among top 200
among the human participants
on Codeforces Competitive
Programming contest.
If we think about
these milestones,
probably they are even very hard
to imagine a couple of months
ago before they
actually happened.
So for this semester, our
course is called Advanced Large
Language Model Agents.
So we will do a deeper dive
into the methodology part,
especially on the
reasoning techniques.
So we will talk about
fundamental techniques
for inference
times [INAUDIBLE]--
for inference times scaling,
training techniques, and also
search and planning.
And for the application
side, we will focus more
on software engineering
and mathematics.
So this includes code generation
and verification, and also
autoformalization
and theorem proving.
After this deep dive
on the methodology,
we will talk about LLM agents
use cases for real world
enterprise application
and also more advanced
agentic workflow design.
And also, topics about
safety and ethics
for real world deployment
of these LLM agents.
Now I will hand over
to our head here, Alex,
to talk about cost logistics.
ALEX PAN: OK.
So the course is pretty
similar to last week's or last
semester's.
The main difference
is we are moving
the lab to a later due date.
So last year the lab
was a bit earlier
and it was so much shorter.
This year, the lab is going
to be-- this semester,
the lab is going to be more
involved and it will be due,
or it will be released
later and you'll
have more time to work on it.
The other main thing, apart
from not having a hackathon,
is we're also going to
open up the project.
So last semester the project
was sort of open-ended.
This time we'll have two
tracks, an applications track
and a research track.
I think I wrote about it here.
So the applications track is
pretty much the same content
as last semester.
The research track is new.
Basically, if you want to or
are interested in submitting
a conference publication
or a workshop publication,
you can apply to
the research track.
We'll have a Google form out
shortly, and if we select you,
then you can work under
the supervision of some
of Don's postdocs
and grad students
to basically try to submit a
workshop paper for this class.
Other than that, everything
else is the same as last year.
I would just refer
to the final--
like, everything is
on this master website
and we won't be
having a syllabus.
Just keep track of the
changes on here and on Edstem.
So that's it for logistics.
XINYUN CHEN: And also,
same as last semester,
we will also invite
very great speakers
to talk about different
topics of advanced LLM agents
methodology and applications.
So we are still finalizing
the guest speaker schedule.
So also check out this course
website for the most up to date
information.
In this lecture, I will talk
about inference time techniques
for LLM reasoning.
So in the intro
of the course, we
will briefly talk
about [? things ?]
like advancement of
reasoning models, which
is kind of one of the highlights
of large language model
development in last year.
And so here I will
go more into details
about what we can see from
these reasoning models.
So on the slides
I'm showing this,
like a result, which was
quoted from the o1 blog.
So from here, we can see that
actually OpenAI o1 model started
to achieve pretty impressive
performance across various very
challenging tasks where
previous models are really
struggling with.
So this includes the
competition level math problems,
like in the AIME
contest last year,
and also competitive programming
contest on Codeforces.
And in the recent o3 results,
they further showed this.
The performance can further
improve with more inference time
compute.
For example, here I'm
showing these curves.
They demonstrated on a
benchmark called ARC-AGI.
So this is a benchmark that
includes a bunch of puzzles
to test how well humans or AI
models can learn some reasoning
patterns, given the
demonstration examples.
So this was a very
challenging task.
So for those existing
models before o1,
if we do not apply any special
inference type techniques
and just do the very
regular inference,
then all existing models
can achieve a less than 25%
accuracy.
Even with o1 model, it can only
achieve around 30% accuracy.
But with the recent o3 model,
if we set the inference time,
like a budget to
around $20 per task,
it can achieve a
performance that kind
of matching the average
human annotators
or mechanical turkers.
And if we further scale out this
inference time cost to a crazy
number like $1,000
to solve one problem,
then actually the model
can achieve 87.5% accuracy.
So definitely this is
a very expensive way
to solve this
particular task, but it
shows how this model can
perform in the ideal case
when we do not care so much
about inference time compute.
Then here on the slides, I'm
showing a very simple OpenAI o1
demo will basically
cause the model
to solve a planning problem.
So what is different
for this o1 model?
So the main difference
is that, for the existing
LLM before the o1 model, when
we enter a user query then
the model will directly
generate this response.
But in the o1 interface, they
include this thought process.
So basically this process can
take different amount of time,
depending on the
difficulty of the task.
For example, for the specific
question I asked the model,
it takes a slightly
more than one minute
to generate the final solution.
And in the o1 interface, they
didn't show the raw thought
process.
Instead, they show a summarized
version of the hidden thought.
So from this hidden thought for
this specific planning problem,
we can see that it summarizes
some key stages in the reasoning
process, including laying
out an initial plan,
evaluating it based on the
model's internal belief,
and then revise the plan so that
it can satisfy the constraints
and improve the optimality.
Then, with the Gemini
2.0 thinking model,
we also make this sort
tokens visible to users.
So on slides, I'm showing a demo
where actually this question
includes an image input.
So this question is--
the math part of this
question is pretty simple.
So basically, there are
four balls in the image,
and the question is asking
the model to take three out
of [? list ?] [? of ?]
numbers so that the sum is 30.
And so the thought here, as
you can see, is a pretty long.
So after we enter the
query, the model immediately
generates these thoughts.
And we don't need to read
the reasoning process
token by token.
I know it's pretty hard to read,
but the most interesting step we
can see from this multi-modal
query is queries that there is
a--
so at the beginning
of this image,
there is a specific
number, which is 9.
So at some point,
the model figures out
a very important step
for this question.
So because if you want
to get the sum of 30,
actually, we need to turn this
9 into 6 by rolling this ball.
So this is a very
interesting feature
of this query when we put
these numbers on some balls.
And also, this
step itself is not
that kind of difficult
mathematically, but actually
it is an interesting trick.
And if we-- earlier,
if we do not
allow the model to
generate this long thought,
this specific step will be
very hard to figure out.
And also like-- besides these
models from OpenAI and Google
DeepMind, there are
other reasoning models
out there recently.
At the beginning of the
lecture, I mentioned,
there are also models from
the DeepSeek team and also
the Kimi team.
And out of all
these breakthrough
in reasoning models,
one core shared idea
is that we need some way to
trigger the large language
model to generate
long chain of thought
before it actually concludes
with the final solution.
In the literature, there
are different approaches
to trigger this
train-of-thought generation.
Like in the original
chain of thought paper,
they designed a
few-shot prompting
scheme, which basically
demonstrates this thought
process in exemplars.
And later on, there
are some works
showing that we can apply
an instruction prompting
to achieve this.
Like, we can use
the instruction,
let's think step by step.
And for the reason
that chat models,
we can see that
even if we do not
give any special
instructions to the model,
the model also tends to generate
some thoughts before coming up
with the final answer, no
matter whether the thought is
short or long.
So there are different ways to
train the model to achieve this.
Like in for instruction
tuning, where
we actually put this
train-of-thought data
into our supervised
fine tuning mixture.
And also what we can see
from recent reasoning models,
we can apply reinforcement
learning to achieve this goal.
In this lecture,
I will focus more
on inference time techniques
for scaling token budget.
And in the future lectures,
we will also dive deeper
into reasoning techniques.
And there will be
some other guest
speakers who will come here
to share their thoughts.
So for this lecture,
I will discuss
three parts about reasoning
techniques at inference time.
I will first discuss the
basic prompting techniques.
And the common idea among
these prompting techniques
is that we want
to allow the model
to use more token budget to
generate a single solution.
Then the second part, I
will talk about techniques
to perform search and selection
from multiple candidates.
And the common idea
here is that if you
want to increase the width to
explore the solution space.
In the last part, I will talk
about iterative self-improvement
will allow the model
to increase its depth
to reach the final solution.
Then, after all these
discussions of different parts,
we will also see how we can best
utilize different combinations
of these techniques
to seek the best
way to utilize the inference
time compute to improve the LLM
reasoning performance.
So let's get started
on the first part
about basic
prompting techniques.
Before we talk about more
advanced prompting techniques,
let's first review
the background
about standard prompting.
So basically in
standard prompting,
let's say we want
to solve a math
problem as shown on the slides,
before the line of works
on chain-of-thought prompting,
the common practice is
that we just put some
question-answer pairs
into the prompt.
Like here.
The question is
the math question,
and the answer is
the final answer.
So before the advancement
in post-training techniques,
if we directly apply
the standard prompting,
then the performance is pretty
poor on reasoning benchmarks.
The fundamental
issue is that if we
look at this standard
future exemplars,
they only provide information
on the final solution format,
but it doesn't tell the
model about the rationale
to derive the solution.
Now we can imagine that
if we are taking a class
and the teachers are
basically just teaching you
with the final, like official
solution without any more
context, then if you do not have
a relative background knowledge
yourself, then it will make your
teaching a lot more difficult.
So for the
chain-of-thought prompting,
the idea is that we will include
these few short exemplars
with sorts.
Again, let's take a
look at this example
of solving math problems.
So here, instead
in exemplars, we
will provide this calculation
steps to basically demonstrate
the model how we should derive
this solution step by step
to achieve the final answer.
Then after giving this
exemplars with chain-of-thought
rationales, then the model
is able to solve this problem
correctly.
In practice, how these
models can benefit more
from chain-of-thought prompting
compared to standard prompting
is also dependent on the model's
fundamental capabilities.
So here on the
slides, I'm showing
the scaling curves presented by
the original chain-of-thought
papers and also some
other related papers
about this chain-of-thought
properties.
So we can see that among the
different model families,
one common trend is that
this CoT performance improves
more significantly with the
increase of the model size.
In particular, if
we look at this gap
of chain-of-thought prompting
versus standard prompting,
then better models benefit
more with CoT generation,
and there, we
suggest improvement
on reasoning performance
once the model
reaches a certain scale.
And I also want to note
that here for these curves,
they are from papers in 2022.
So these experiments are done
using pre-trained only LLMs.
So this is why it is
important to apply
some prompting so that
the model can generate
the results immediately.
And also with this recent
post-training techniques,
they might show some
different scaling curves
like we have seen some
strong but very lightweight
LLMs recently.
But the main conclusions
will still hold.
We will still see
this overall trend.
Basically, once the
model becomes better,
it will benefit more
from this allowance
of the train-of-thought
generation.
Then in the follow up work
called large language models
are zero-shot reasoners.
They further find that even with
pre-trained only large language
models, we do not have to
provide a model with exemplars
to elicit these CoT generation.
Instead, we can achieve
this with an instruction.
Like in the paper, they
demonstrate this instruction.
Let's think step by step.
Then, after we apply
this instruction,
before we ask the model
to generate the answer,
the model can also
generate some thoughts
before generating
the final solution.
And they empirically
they demonstrate
that this zero-shot
CoT significantly
outperforms zero-shot
performance, especially
on harder, like, mass and
symbolic reasoning tasks.
So zero-shot CoT is more
convenient than few-shot CoT
in the sense that we no longer
need to manually annotate
source ourselves as exemplars.
But if we compare
their performance,
zero-shot CoT
performance is still
much worse than few-shot CoT.
Then, a very natural
question I want to ask
is, how can we get the
best of both worlds?
How to CoT performance without
manually labeling samplers?
So this is what
we want to achieve
with our paper, large language
models, as analogical reasoners.
And this paper was
published at ICLR last year.
The idea is that, instead of
directly providing the model
with exemplars, we
instruct the model
to first record
relevant exemplars
to solve the test problem.
Then, based on this model
generated examplars,
then the model will try to
solve the test problems.
Just imagine that these are
self-generated exemplars
are just some CoT examples
provided by external sources.
The benefit of this
design lies in two folds.
First, these exemplars
are self-generated
by the large language models,
so we fulfill our original goal.
We don't need to do any
manual labeling here.
On the other hand,
because this instruction
is applied to each
test question,
so basically for
different test question,
the model is able to generate
different exemplars which
are more relevant to the
concrete topics covered
in the test question.
So these exemplars are more
tailored to individual problems.
We call our approach
analogical prompting,
because this
methodology is actually
can be motivated by human
analogical reasoning.
If we think about
few-shot prompting,
it is not supernatural
if we think about it
in the human reasoning
way, because humans are not
explicitly given
demonstrations every time
for each single new problem.
And instead, humans also
intrinsically recall
from past relevant experience.
So in a classic reasoning
methodology book
called How to Solve
It from Polya,
they have a very nice
description about this reasoning
method named, do
a related problem?
So the idea is that
when solving a problem,
we look for a pre-formally
solved problem, which
is linked to our present one by
generalization, specialization,
or analogy.
And we want to learn from these
past results or their methods,
so that it can help us solve
new task problems better.
If we think about it from the
human reasoning perspective,
then besides
exemplars, we can also
instruct a model to
generate some higher level
knowledge, which can be a
more better summary of what we
need to solve the new problems.
And this generated knowledge
can complement the problems
with broader insights.
So here, let's take solving
coding problems as an example.
So given a new
coding problem, we
can first instruct the
model to self generate
some knowledge, which
is more of higher level
tutorial about the algorithms
we need to solve the problem.
And also, the model
needs to identify
what are the main algorithms
we need so that it can come up
with related
examples of problems
with their corresponding code.
Then after this instruction, and
also once the model generated
has related a background
knowledge including higher level
tutorial and exemplars,
then the model
goes back to solve the
initial test problem.
So in the results, we show
that basically analogical
prompting not only
outperforms zero-shot CoT,
but it actually outperforms
manual few-shot CoT as well.
And we show this performance
improvement on a math problem
solving, code
generation, and also
like BIG-Bench reasoning tasks.
If you look at these
results at the first time,
you might be a bit surprised
because knowledge here,
all these examples of
problems or knowledge,
are generated by the model.
So intuitively it might
contain more errors
than human annotated exemplars.
Empirically, we indeed
observe this trend.
We see that, for example, for
low stack exemplars generated
by the model for math problems,
around 70% of them are accurate,
and also they are relevant.
But the rest can
have some issues,
they are completely irrelevant,
or there are some actually wrong
calculation steps.
But even so, there are some
noises in the demonstrations.
The model still
benefits a lot from it.
So given this like a finding,
you might imagine that this
means at least the model
should be able to generate some
reasonable exemplars, or
otherwise it cannot learn from
it at all.
So based on this
intuition, we also
conduct a pretty
rough scaling study
for this analogical prompting.
So here we are comparing
models among different--
among the GPT text
model families.
I know these models are all
shut down and deprecated now,
but this trend will still hold.
So basically, we can see
that weaker large language
models benefit less from
analogical prompting.
Although if we compare
the performance
to zero-shot
train-of-thought, it is on par
or still outperforms
their performance.
And with stronger
language models,
starting from text adventure
002 in the GPT family,
analogical prompting starts
to outperform chain-of-thought
prompting with manually
designed exemplars.
And notice that actually,
this approach can even
outperform retrieved exemplars.
So for retrieval
method, what we did
is that basically for
each test problem,
we implement a
retrieval approach
so that it will find those
most relevant problems
in the least like GSM8K
mass corpus training data.
So one explanation here
is that this generated
train-of-thought by the
model can be more tailored
to the underlying
reasoning style of these,
like pre-trained or instruction
tuned large language models.
So this finding actually is also
in line with the recent trend,
when we are trying to develop
the reasoning models instead
of putting human
written thoughts,
we can have some
training methods
so that the model is able to
discover the best like reasoning
strategies by itself.
Now let's go back
to the instruction.
Let's think step by step.
So why do we have to
use this sentence?
Is there something
special about it?
So in the original
zero-shot CoT paper,
they conducted
this ablation study
of different variants
of these instructions
to trigger the
train-of-thought generation.
So some of them do
not make much sense.
So it is, not surprising that
they do not perform well.
But if we look at those
different instructions
in the top category,
instructive,
If we mask out this
accuracy numbers,
it might be not that intuitive
know which instruction
should be performed better.
And it can be kind of
not very good to see
that even if you just
change a couple of words,
then the accuracy number can
change very dramatically.
So this shows that current
large models are pretty
sensitive to prompt design.
And because-- and
also in many cases,
there is no clear
principle about how
to write optimal performance.
And this is why
nowadays there are still
many people who are
writing a lot of guidelines
about how to have the
best practice to do
prompt engineering.
So given this observation,
a very natural question
I want to ask next is, how we
can reduce this manual work
for writing prompts?
So one idea is that
since our large models
can solve many challenging
reasoning problems
and also answering
other queries,
so why don't we
also use it to help
us do the prompt engineering
or prompt design in general?
So in ICLR 2023 there is a paper
called Large Language Models are
Human Level Prompt Engineers.
So the high level
idea is basically
to apply a large model
to propose prompts,
so that we hope
this model generated
prompts can also perform even
better than human written
prompts.
So here I'm showing LLM complete
diagram of their method.
So there are two
important stages.
The first is this the
proposal generation
where we can leverage
this large language
model to generate initial
instructions, given our task
description.
Then once the model generate
different proposed prompts,
then we'll score
each instruction
based on the
prediction correctness
on a small set of problems.
So here, basically
we will hold out
a small validation
set, which can tell us
the quality of each prompt.
So here the setup
might be more similar
to the traditional
machine learning task
where we have this separation
of training and test.
But actually we do not need to
include so many examples here
for this validation purpose.
Like in most cases, it
is sufficient to include
tens of examples or just
around 100 problems.
Then in our work published
at ICLR last year,
we go further where we try to
use this [? language ?] model,
not only just to propose
some instructions
and do some kind of a
search and mutation,
we also want to apply it as an
optimizer to iteratively improve
the prompt.
So the idea of our
approach is that we
want to instruct the LLM to
leverage the past or partition
trajectory represented as
sorted solution score pairs,
so that it can learn
to iteratively generate
better prompts with more steps.
So in this work, we frame it
as a more general optimization
framework in the
natural language space.
But in this specific use
case of prompt optimization,
basically this
means that we will
have two large language models
as optimizers and evaluators.
So basically this optimizer
is the language model,
which is responsible
for proposing
a new instruction, given old
ones and also the task samplers.
And the evaluator
is the scholar,
which will evaluate the accuracy
or performance of a given
instruction.
Now let's take a look at how
we can design a meta-prompt
to achieve this goal.
So on the slides,
I'm showing you
an example,
meta-prompt for GSM8K
to solve the math problems.
The prompt itself
looks pretty long,
but basically there are
two main components.
The first one is this
[? text ?] trajectory,
including the instructions we
have explored in the past steps,
and with their
corresponding accuracies.
And in practice, we will sort
them in the ascending order
and we can remove
those older ones
if the context is not enough to
put all of them in the history.
And we also provide
this exemplars
to show what's the task
we want to optimize.
And basically here, for
example, for math problems
we only need to include this QA
pairs and with the final answer.
So again, there's
no need to annotate
any train-of-thought or
any explanations of how
we can derive this solution.
Then for the results,
basically, again we
are testing all
these instructions
on pre-trained only
large language models.
And we use prompt
tool at that time.
And we also try using different
models as optimizers including
PaLM model and the GPT model.
So for all these
approaches, we are
starting from the initial
instruction with let's solve
the problem, which achieves
an accuracy of around 61%
for this GSM8K task.
And this is a pretty
general purpose instruction.
It is around 10% lower
than the instruction
let's see step by step.
And if we look at the
best LLM generative prompt
among this list, we can see that
actually this instruction takes
a deep breath and work on
this problem step by step.
Achieves around 8% like low--
like higher than this, let's
think, step by step instruction.
And actually if you compare this
performance to few-shot CoT,
it matches the performance
reported in the PaLM 2 paper,
where the train-of-thought
examplars are written by humans.
So there are two things
we can think about here.
One is that basically here
where I seeing another way
to basically achieve very
competitive performance
to few-shot CoT, we
saw that manually
writing examples ourselves.
Another perspective is that
with this type of LLM based
prompt optimization, it
doesn't only save us time to
so that we do not need to spend
so much time to manually tune
the prompts ourselves.
But actually, when it
comes up with new prompts,
it also provides sometimes
surprising different angles.
Like I can assume
that, for example,
like [INAUDIBLE]
take a deep breath.
At least for me, if I'm trying
to revise the prompt by myself,
I won't feel that this phrase
will be so, so helpful,
but empirically, the large
model with this optimization
loop actually it
can somehow come up
with this instruction that fits
pretty well for this model.
And note that, in
this [? text ?]
LLM-based optimization
process, actually,
this is not a real
optimization in the sense
that we do not have
any training here.
It is completely prompting only.
So there's no guarantee that the
model can just keep coming up
with better and better prompts.
But in practice, we find that,
actually, this optimization
curve holds for
different models.
So we can see that basically
with more optimization
steps, which is basically this
iterative prompting steps,
the accuracy increases with
more steps and then plateaus.
So it looks pretty like similar
to the traditional optimization
graphs.
OK.
Now let's go back
to Chain-of-Thought.
So from the methodology
perspective,
what does Chain-of-Thought
really bring into our reasoning?
Why is it so effective?
If we think about it,
Chain-of-Thought prompting
is basically giving
us a way to perform
this variable computation
of the process, which
will lead the number
of tokens used
for problem will be adapted to
task of different difficulty
levels.
So if we think about standard
prompting, basically,
for the same task, if the
answer learns are the same,
then basically, if we just
provide the final answer
directly, it basically means
that we are forcing the model
to use the same amount of time,
same amount of inference time
budget to solve each problem,
regardless of its difficulty.
But with this, like
a Chain-of-Thought,
basically, it shows that
for more complex questions,
because it also require more
reasoning steps to solve
the problem, like
for math problems,
it might require more
calculation steps.
So basically, with this
Chain-of-Thought idea,
it allows the model to
also perform more reasoning
steps in the token space
so that it can better
solve the task problems.
And in the
Chain-of-Thought paper,
they also show that even if
the difficulty of the problems
is in the exemplars are
pretty simple math problems,
but actually, the
same problem can also
generalize to test problems
that require much more reasoning
steps.
Then, if we think about the
high level reasoning strategies,
Chain-of-Thought also
incorporates a lot
of reasoning process that are
very important for us humans
to reason about difficult task
such as decomposition, planning,
and et cetera.
So if you want to further
improve the model performance,
and especially if
we know what are
some good guidelines on
the reasoning strategies
we need to use for
a specific task,
we can also explicitly
instruct the LLM
with the desired reasoning
strategies for problem solving.
So one idea to further push
this decomposition strategy
is called least-to-most
prompting.
And the goal of this
approach is to achieve
easy-to-hard generalization
by explicitly telling
the model what's the best
practice to decompose
the original problem.
So in the slides, I'm
showing this example
for solving math problems.
And basically, in this original
least-to-most prompting paper
from my colleagues
at Google DeepMind,
it includes two stages.
So in the first stage, it
performs the problem reduction.
Like given a math problem,
it first reduces the problems
into simpler subproblems.
So each sub math problem
can be easier to solve,
requires fewer
calculation steps.
Then given this
subquestions the model
will be able to sequentially
solve these subproblems
and combine the solutions to
solve the original problem.
The most impressive results from
this work is that, actually,
with this least-to-most
prompting design,
it shows for the first time
that we do not need to design
a [? neural-symbolic ?]
frameworks or requiring any
program execution.
But it can still solve this
compositional generalization
benchmarks with nearly
perfect accuracy.
So the results show in their
paper is on this SCAN benchmark.
So SCAN is a synthetic
data about translating
programmatically
generated natural language
commands into action sequences.
The most challenging
part of this benchmark
is about this length split.
Basically, in their
[? text ?] splits,
all the action
sequences are longer
than the training samples.
So this makes it
very challenging
for the traditional like
sequence-to-sequence
learning if we directly do this
training on their training set.
And then on this, length
split, the test accuracy
will be no more
than 25% unless we
apply some neural-symbolic
techniques.
But then basically, with
least-to-most prompting,
they show that if they
use the latest models
at that time, which is
the code-davinci-002,
they are able to achieve
nearly perfect test accuracy.
And at the same
time, they only need
to use 0.1% of the training
samples as exemplars.
So it is both test
efficient or data efficient
to adapt to new tasks
while also the performance
is very competitive.
Learning our follow up work
published at ICLR last year,
we further show that we can
extend this least-to-most
prompting idea to
solve more complicated
compositional generalization
in the case of translating text
to more realistic
programming languages.
Like here on the slides,
I'm showing this example
of translating natural language
questions to SPARQL queries.
So the main challenge here
is that for more real world
languages, including natural
language or programming
languages, there are more
complicated grammar rules
and also the vocabulary
size is larger.
This means that,
especially, if we do not
have a model with a
super long context,
then a single prompt
will be no longer
enough to cover all the grammar
rules needed to solve the task.
So actually, with
this challenge,
it shows one benefit
of decomposition
by allowing the model
to use different prompts
for different reasoning stages.
It also enables the model
to use customized prompts
for each subproblem
or each subtask
in the context of
agent development.
So here is an overview of our
dynamic least-to-most prompting
approach.
So some details do not
matter too much here like how
we do the decomposition.
But the [? menu ?]
stage we add is
this so-called dynamic
selection of exemplars
for each subproblem.
So basically here, for each
of test, like a sentence,
we can discover those
example questions
with the most relevant
grammar rules.
So basically, we can assure that
for each part of the sentence,
we can always retrieve for
the most useful grammar rules
to solve the task so that the
model can have enough context
to solve the problem.
So all these compositional
[? three ?] [? base ?] question
benchmark, the CFQ data set.
Again, we show that, actually,
our dynamic least-to-most
prompting approach outperforms
all these baselines, which
where we need to train a model
on the complete training set.
And again, if we compare this
dynamic least-to-most prompting
with Chain-of-Thought prompting
and other prompting approaches,
it also scales better when
we increase this examplar
[? problem ?] to generate
these few-shot [? examplars. ?]
So far, we have talked about
how we can instruct the model
to solve the problem in some
like with some reasoning
strategies indicated by
the few-shot examplars.
But if we think about
it, we can assume
that for different
reasoning tasks,
they can require very
different reasoning structures.
Like there will
be different ways
to decompose the task
and plan for each stage.
At the same time,
we might not want
to annotate all these best
practices for each type of task.
Again, we don't want to do this
manual labeling of exemplars
for every single problem.
So in our self-discover work, we
published at NeurIPS last year,
we basically instruct
the model to compose
task-specific reasoning
structures without manually
written demonstrations.
So in practice, how we do
it is that basically, we
will list a kind of
[INAUDIBLE] of best practice
of reasoning
strategies, including
like a Chain-of-Thought
reasoning, doing decomposition,
doing some
self-reflection, et cetera,
then given a
different, a new task,
the model will think about how
it can utilize the reasoning
strategies that are best
suited for the current task
and compose the
reasoning structure.
Follow it to solve the problem.
And for evaluation, we also show
that with this self-discovery
methodology, it outperforms
Chain-of-Thought prompting
and also, other baselines
on different benchmarks,
including BIG-Bench-Hard
reasoning task,
[? MATH ?] benchmark, and
also some other benchmarks
for [? socio-agent ?] reasoning.
So to summarize, in the
first part I talked about,
I first talked about
Chain-of-Thought generation.
And the fundamental idea
of allowing the model
to perform variable computation
to trigger the thought process.
And this thought process
can adapt to tasks
of different difficulty levels.
And we talked about
how to improve
the Chain-of-Thought
performance at inference time.
So in the original
Chain-of-Thought paper,
we talk about the
few-shot prompting idea
with labeling of thoughts.
And we talked about
instruction prompting
to trigger this
Chain-of-Thought generation.
And also, we talked about how
we can instruct a large language
model to automate
the prompt design
and discover better
problems by themselves.
So notice that
this best practice
of interacting with
large language models
can evolve over time.
Like for example, recently with
this [? post-trained ?] large
language models, you do not
have to put exemplars for every
single task for the model
to learn how to do it.
And for some models, for
example, it is better for you
to just provide very clear
guidelines and instructions
on what you want.
And then hope the model can
just follow your instructions.
And some models prefer those
like an interactive discussion
and some models might prefer
just a very long and detailed
instruction at once.
But the principles
of how to discover
good prompting strategies for
reasoning still hold here.
Like two very
important criteria is
that we want this approach
to encourage the model
to generate longer
Chain-of-Thought
for complex tasks.
We want it to scale with
different task difficulty.
And also, we need this
prompting technique
to be able to support
reasoning strategies required
for the task.
So now, let's start
the second part
about perform
search and selection
from multiple candidates
and increasing the width
to explore the solution space.
So after we talk about the first
part, what is missing so far?
Yeah, I guess this
question is not
so hard since I already showed
the outline of this slides.
So basically, from
first part, we
can see that we should not
limit the large language
model to generate only
one solution per problem.
Because the model can just
have some mistakes in its
[? single-pass ?] solution.
Instead, we should
allow the model
to explore multiple
branches, which
will allow the large language
model to recover from mistakes
in a single generation.
And there are two ways
to basically increase
the width of this
solution exploration.
One is that we can
generate multiple candidate
solutions per problem.
Another is that,
at each step, we
can allow the model to generate
multiple potential next
reasoning steps.
It is not that hard to think
that with this multiple sample
generation, then the upper
bound of the performance
will be definitely
higher because we
allow the model to
select an alternative,
probably better solution.
But the fundamental challenge
for approaches along this line
is that how to select
the best response
from multiple candidates.
Because in the real
world use case,
we do not have an Oracle
Scholar at inference time.
So surely, for example,
in the chat interface,
we can just have
the model generate
multiple solutions and the user
can pick whatever they want.
Then this is kind of a best
of [? selection ?] case.
But it will be more ideal
if the model can just
do this kind of
process internally
so that we do not have to
review like tens of solutions
by ourselves to
select what we want.
So along the line
of these ideas,
I want to first talk about
this self-consistency work
from my colleagues
at Google DeepMind.
So if we look at
this idea nowadays,
we will find that this is
an incredibly simple idea.
But it is actually
very effective.
And it actually can
improve performance a lot
with all the different models.
So let's say we want to
also solve a math problem.
And this time, we
allow the model
to generate multiple responses.
So basically, after we
have all these responses,
we still do not know
which one is accurate.
But here, we have
this consistency
based selection criterion.
So basically, if let's
say for this math problem
with a single number
as the final answer,
we will look at these
three solutions.
Two of them have the answer 18
and of them have the answer 26.
So basically 18 is the
most consistent answer.
So we pick the response
corresponding to this.
Like most frequently
appeared answer.
And note that here,
one important thing
is that this selection is only
based on the final answer.
It is not based on
the reasoning process.
The model can come
up with whatever
reasoning process it wants.
So as long as they lead
to the same final answer,
we consider them to be all good.
This is a pretty simple idea.
But actually, it
boosts the performance
across different
models and benchmarks.
And here, in their
paper, they also--
I evaluate all the models
available at that time,
and especially on math problems.
They show very significant
performance improvement.
Now let's talk about
this scaling effect
again with the
self-consistency approach.
So for the baseline
here in the curves,
they compare with
sample-and-rank baseline.
This is actually a
pretty natural baseline,
which says that we can select
the response with the highest
log probability.
So then here, the assumption is
that if the model gives higher
probability to the
current response,
it should be more
confident about it.
But actually, if we
look at these curves,
we can see that self-consistency
performance scales much better
than probability-based ranking.
So it's more and more responses,
like up to 40 responses.
Self-consistency performance
is still improving.
But these
sample-and-rank baseline
has already stopped improving
around 10 responses already.
But there is an exception.
So the exception is
that, if we train
the model to be a very good
verifier for the task we care
about, we might be able
to outperform this scaling
curve with self-consistency.
And we will talk about it later.
Another very
important factor that
contributes to
self-consistency success
is that we need the model to
generate very diverse responses
to perform this
consistency-based selection.
So here, basically
in this results,
they also compare with
different baselines.
So the beam search is actually
a very classic search algorithm
like in the NLP literature
before the [? LLM ?] error.
So basically, the idea is
that at each decoding step,
we will keep the top
[? k ?] like tokens
with the highest probabilities.
Then in the end, we will use
a sentence with the highest
overall probability.
And then they also compare with
this [? sample ?] baselines,
where they apply greedy decoding
among different variants of how
you formulate the prompt.
Because earlier we
mentioned that the LLMs are
sensitive to different prompts.
Also, they compare the
performance to different ways
to permute the exemplars
orders in the prompt.
So again, they show
that self-consistency
using sampling scales
better with more samples.
So the important factor here is
that basically for the sampling
method, it needs to ensure that
the responses are very diverse.
So we can do this sampling
with a high temperature.
Or we can perform
nucleus sampling
by setting the parameters
in the right way
to enforce this
diversity, et cetera.
One analysis from this work is
actually pretty interesting.
It is related to
model calibration.
So this is about
actually how does
this consistency-based selection
improve the model performance.
What does it mean when the
model, for a given task,
the model can come up with
a more consistent response?
So here, they show
this curve to show
the correlation between the
accuracy and consistency.
So here, we can see
that if it follows,
sample responses,
if more of them
lead to the same
final answer, this
means that this consistency
percentage is higher.
Then there are two conclusions
we can see from here.
One is that this
large language model
is more certain with its
final predicted conclusion
even if they are coming up
with the same conclusion
with different
reasoning process.
And empirically, we see that
this aggregated solution
for this, more consistent
[? text ?] responses,
can be more likely
to be accurate.
The final solution can
just be the right one
for the original test problem.
So this can also explain
why this consistency can
be a very simple,
but very powerful
criterion to select
the final solution.
So in the
self-consistency paper,
they demonstrate this approach
on those test-based reasoning
problems.
And actually, this
consistency-based selection
approach is also very
powerful for code generation.
And in our AlphaCode
work at Google DeepMind,
this AlphaCode system itself
is a pretty complicated one.
It includes the model training
and inference time techniques.
But here, I will mainly focus
on this inference stage called
filtering and clustering.
And especially, this
clustering is basically tries
to do this like a code selection
based on the consistency
[? of ?] execution results.
So let's first briefly
discuss about the background,
the problem setting of
competitive programming.
So basically, in a competitive
programming problem,
in the problem
description, it will
include a very long
and complicated task
to tell about the
background story,
about what we want
for the problem
for the corresponding code.
And then also, it includes
a few input-output pairs
as test cases.
Then for the solution to
be considered correct,
the generated code needs
to pass both the given test
cases in the prompt.
And also, usually, we will
have some held-out test cases.
And these test cases are
typically of larger scale
and they will be more difficult
than this example test cases.
And they will cover
some corner cases.
So since we already have
some [? input ?] examples,
we can filter the programs
that fail the given test
cases already.
But for the remaining
programs, they
might still fail on the
held-out test cases.
Like for those of you who have
participated in these coding
contests, you might
feel the same way.
You feel that your
code is great.
But it just fail on some
mysterious held-out test cases
and you didn't get
the score you want.
So basically, for the
AlphaCode system, what we do
is that we will train an LLM
model to generate new test
inputs for these test problems.
Then we will execute
those like sample programs
on all these model
generated inputs.
And then we cluster all programs
with the same outputs together.
The assumption here
is basically if we
have the model to generate
enough number of test inputs.
And also, they are
diverse of higher quality.
Then actually, we can
assume that all programs
in the same cluster
are semantically
equivalent because they lead
to the same execution results.
And then finally, we
sample one program
from each of the 10
largest clusters.
In our [? evaluation, ?] we show
that this clustering provides
additional performance
gain compared
to the filter only method.
But clearly, there is still a
gap from the Oracle selection.
Because there's
still no guarantee
that the consistent response
will be just the best
one out of the candidate pools.
Now let's revisit this
self-consistency decoding
pipeline.
So one limitation
here is that for
the original self-consistency,
we need an answer extraction
process so that we can do this
aggregation among the candidate
responses.
So if we want to apply
this consistency based
decoding to broader used cases,
the natural next question
is how we can do it for
free-form generation, where
it is not that natural to have
this aggregation and answer
extraction process?
So this is we want to
achieve with our work
on universal self-consistency.
The idea is that, instead of
having this answer extraction
process, we ask the large
language model to perform
consistency-based selection.
So specifically, we
throw an instruction
to the model asking it to select
the most consistent response
based on the majority consensus.
And also, it needs to take a
look at all these candidate
responses.
So the intuition here
is that, clearly, we
know that it will be hard for
the model to judge the answer
correctness by itself.
But consistency should be a
simpler criterion to measure.
Then empirically,
we also evaluate
this universal
self-consistency method
for different applications.
So for [? low-stack, ?]
free-form generation problems,
like summarization and
question answering,
we stack low [? factual ?]
like final answers.
We see that the universal
self-consistency also still
can improve over
the baselines, where
the original self-consistency
is not directly applicable.
An old math reasoning
and coding problems
where we can apply this
original self-consistency idea.
Actually, universal
self-consistency
can match its performance
without the requirement
of performing this answer
extraction and code execution.
And notice here, clearly,
this universal self-consistent
performance is bounded by
the long-context capability.
So at that time, we are
using an earlier model,
which is not super great
at long-context reasoning.
So we can see that when
we include more responses
in the prompt, the
performance might not
go up as well as the
original self-consistency.
But we can see that with
the recent development
of long-context models.
This will allow such kind of
model-based selection approach
to scale more with
more responses.
And also, in practice,
for most tasks,
it can be well-solved
within, let's say,
a 10 responses in
the candidate pool.
So this will still showcase the
usability of this model based
consistency selection.
Previously, we talked about,
for the model-based selection,
using the log probability
from the original model,
this approach of ranking
doesn't scale better
than the consistency-based
selection.
So to improve further over this
consistency-based selection,
one idea is that we can
train a large language
model as the ranker.
And we hope that at
least this ranker
can perform better than this
simple consistency criterion.
And actually, it can have some
kind of sense of which responses
are more likely to be accurate.
So here, on the slides,
I'm showing this diagram
from the original
OpenAI paper, which
introduced the GSM8K data set.
And also, they
demonstrate this method
of how to train a verifier to
show the-- to basically judge
the correctness of
the matched solution.
And also, later on, they have
this follow up paper called
"Let's Verify Step by Step."
So in total, for this line
of LLM-based ranking works,
there are two ways to
design the LLM-based method
to judge the answer quality.
The first way is the most--
the initial and the most
standard approach, which is
called outcome-supervised
reward model.
Basically, it will
verify the correctness
at the solution level.
Like given a math problem,
the solution, the model
will tell you whether the
solution is correct or not.
Another approach introduced in
this "Let's Verify Step by Step"
paper is called
process-supervised reward model.
So the idea is that, instead of
verifying [? LLMs ?] solution
space, we can also
very, at a step level,
we can see whether
each step is accurate.
So in their work, they show that
this process-supervised reward
model actually scales
better with more samples
compared to this outcome-based
reward model and also
this majority voting baseline.
But clearly, here,
the performance
will be highly dependent
on the verifier quality.
And also, the same
verifier might not
generalize across tasks.
Because we know that this
consistency-based criterion is
very simple and actually can be
directly applied to many tasks.
But for these
[? rank ?] models, you
need to design a good
training strategy
and also design a good training
data so that it can really
work across different
domains you care about.
So far, we have talked
about response selection
only at the solution level.
So we only perform
this selection
after the full
responses are generated.
But assuming that we have a
very good step-wise scorer,
then actually, this
solution-based response
selection is a waste of
using this step-wise scorer.
Because actually, we can
do more with such kind
of a more powerful and
more fine-grained verifier.
So if we really have this good
step-wise scorer function,
then actually, we can
perform this tree search
with large language model.
Where basically, instead of
waiting until the solution
becomes complete, during
the search process,
we can prioritize those
exploration of partial solutions
at the step level.
And we can explore
more promising steps
before exploring
other [? processes. ?]
So on the slides, I'm
showing this list,
like diagram from the Tree
of Thought prompting paper.
So from this illustration,
you can clearly
see what are the differences
of different prompting methods.
Like Chain-of-Thought
prompting is basically a train.
This self-consistency method is
like multiple parallel chains.
And then for this
Train of Thought,
basically, at each step, it
can have multiple branches
to explore the next step.
And you don't have to
complete all these step
passes until the end.
So here, I will
show this how we can
apply this Tree of Thought idea
with a simple example of game
of 24.
So basically, at
each step, there
are two important
stages we want to do.
One is called
thought generation.
Basically, in this step, we will
prompt the large language model
to propose possible
next thinking steps.
Like in the game of 24,
these next thinking steps
are pretty simple in format.
You just need to
select the two numbers
to perform this calculation.
Then there is another stage
called thought evaluation.
Where again, here, we can
perform the large language
model to evaluate how
promising the current state is.
Like for the game
of 24, you need
to decide whether it is possible
to reach the final number of 24
after the list, all
the manipulations.
So previously, we show how--
we can show how we
can do this [? text ?]
evaluation at step level.
So it will determine the
quality of each individual step.
But related to our previous
consistency-based selection
discussion for this
scoring function,
we can also think
about it as a way
to just select the best
state among the candidates.
We don't need to
just have the model
to make this decision
at the point level.
So the idea is that we
can ask the large language
model to select the
best responses among all
these possible next steps.
And then, we can also do
this voting multiple times.
Because since all
these [INAUDIBLE]
here is based on large
language model sampling.
Then with all these
different votes,
the model can finally
select the majority vote
as the final choice to proceed.
Here, for the results,
I'm showing the list again
of 24 evaluation.
And in the original paper, they
also show some other benchmarks.
So we can see that
with Tree of Thought
using breadth-first
search, it scales
better than the standard
prompting and Chain-of-Thought
with respect to token budget.
And going further, clearly, we
can integrate some more advanced
search algorithms.
Like in this original
Tree of Thought paper,
they use the most basic BFS
and [? DFS ?] algorithms.
But in the later one,
we also see some papers
which are coming up with these
Monte-Carlo Tree Search methods.
And some works are also trying
to train a separate evaluation
function instead of just
prompting the model.
Again here, the
important consideration
is that we need to design
a good language model
and prompting scheme
so that it can be
effective for self-evaluation.
So to summarize, in
this second part,
I show that we can further
scale this inference time
compute by sampling multiple
branches in the solution space.
And we talked about
consistency-based selection,
which is a pretty simple, but
effective and general principle.
We talked about this
self-consistency,
where we can marginalize
out reasoning processes
and do the selection-based
on the final answer.
And for code generation, we
can also do this reranking
based on execution consistency.
When this large language
model self-evaluation
works well so that
it can really judge
the quality of partial
solutions or structure quality
at a step level.
We can also apply
this search method.
And in this case, sometimes,
it will scale better.
And also, it can
reduce the token cost
because it can already
eliminates those nonpromising
[? process ?] during
the mean time.
So finally, I will talk about
iterative self-improvement,
which will try to
increase the depth
to reach the final solution.
So even with the most
recent advanced models,
including those
recent models, we
can see that they can achieve
pretty amazing numbers
on those competitive and
challenging benchmarks
for solving hard maths
and coding questions.
But they can still, sometimes,
make pretty obvious mistakes
and people are keeping
complaining about it.
But if you think
about us as humans,
we also tend to make sometimes
pretty trivial mistakes
at first thought.
So previously, we talked about
we can sample multiple solutions
to help us reduce these mistakes
from a single prediction.
But if we think
about it again, it
is actually a pretty suboptimal
way to do this error correction.
Because all these responses
are generated in parallel.
So we do not really learn
from the past mistakes,
we can just have
the model generate
the same wrong predictions
again and again.
So basically, in this part about
inference time self-improvement,
I will talk about techniques
using large language models
to iteratively improve its own
response for the given task.
And also, this will
align better with us
humans like an error
correction process.
So the first papers
about these ideas
include this like
reflection and self-refine.
So basically, in
this process, there
are also two important steps
after generating each solution.
So basically, after the
model generates the solution,
the model will also
generate some feedback
based on what it observes.
And in this step, it can use
those external evaluation
when available.
So for example, in the
original reflection paper,
they focus more on this
agentic setup, where basically,
the LLM, as the agent
will propose actions
to the environment.
And the environment will
give the model some kind
of changes of the observations.
So this will be
external signal to tell
the model whether the current
[? state ?] is promising.
Then based on this model
generated reflection feedback
and also these
external observations,
then this large language
model will refine its output
to revise this next
prediction step given
both this internal
and external signals.
In this reflection
paper, they show
that this self-reflection
and self-refinement
works pretty well, especially
when we can have a scheme.
So that basically, the model
can utilize pretty high quality
evaluation or when the external
signals are very reliable.
So for example, in the
case of a ALFWorld,
it is an agent, like
a navigation task.
So there will be clear signals
about observations at each step.
And they also evaluate on
their approach on HotPotQA.
But they kind of
repurpose this QA task
into an agent environment.
In the sense that after the
model generates the solution,
they assume that
this environment
will give a signal about whether
the current solution is correct
or not.
This is why you can keep seeing
this improvement with more
trials.
And we will revisit
this assumption later.
And if we think about this
like self-improvement loop
for applications,
then code generation
is actually a pretty
natural used case.
Because when we are writing
code, for us for example,
we also debug our code
better within an IDE.
And we do not just write
the code and we stop.
We actually really rely
on this interactive loop
when we are trying to
investigate all these code
execution, results.
And see whether it makes
sense and also which
parts we should revise later.
And this is also
one fundamental idea
of the recent coding agents.
So in our paper
of self-debugging,
we also do a deeper dive into
what kind of feedback formats
will be helpful for the model to
better correct its own mistakes.
So for example, the most
simple feedback message
is basically a short
universal information
about whether a current
code is correct or not
without more information.
And then for unit
test feedback, we also
include the execution results.
Like whether the current
unit test has passed
or whether there are
any runtime errors.
Then for code explanation,
basically, at each step,
we also ask the model to
self-generate some line
by line explanation
of the implementation
in natural language.
So this idea is that kind
of a motivated by human
[INAUDIBLE] debugging,
trying to ask the model
to see what it's trying
to do in the code.
And finally, in
the trace feedback.
Basically, we ask the
model to perform some line
by line simulation of the
execution trace by itself.
This is also one way of
debugging by human programmers.
Empirically, we evaluated the
latest large language models
at the time of paper
publication last year.
So basically, we can see that
with this self-debugging loop,
it consistently
improves the performance
across different
large language models
of different capabilities.
And also, if we give more
informative feedback,
it can further improve
the debugging performance.
Now let's go back to this
self-correction for question
answering tasks.
Previously, we talked about
these results of HotPotQA.
And also, in some
other works, it also
show this improvement
of self-correction
on other reasoning task
like math problem solving.
But all of these
significant improvement
comes from the assumption
with an Oracle verifier.
But in practice,
this Oracle verifier
will not be available
in many scenarios.
Especially, in the case of
solving, reasoning problems.
You can imagine that when
you are taking a math test,
you don't really have the
official solution at hand.
Otherwise, it will
be just trivial
for you to finish the exam.
So basically, the question
here we want to study
is how do these
large language models
perform if we do not
give the model such very
explicit and accurate external
feedback about the response
correctness.
So in our paper published
last year at ICLR called Large
Language Models Cannot
Self-Correct Reasoning Yet,
we actually show some negative
results from this study.
So we compare with
this Oracle baseline,
where we utilize the ground
truth answer for question.
And same as previous works,
we show this huge improvement.
Then we studied the case of
the real self-correction,
where we do not allow the model
to utilize any Oracle feedback.
The model needs to judge
the response correctness
by themselves.
Then these are the results,
we show in the bottom table.
We can see that
the main issue here
is that because large
language models can only
judge the correctness
of its predictions,
it often turns an
originally correct solution
into a wrong one.
So this is why actually
in this self-correction
without external
evaluation, this process
can lead to worse
performance after each round.
So with this study,
one natural question
is probably we didn't tune
the feedback prompt well
so this is why it fails.
So to address this
question, we also
design several variants
of this feedback prompt.
And notice that all
these feedback prompts
are pretty general.
They are not specific
tuned for one task.
So we can see that if we just
have this simple general-purpose
feedback prompt, if we do not
have any more of the model
training, then editing this
feedback prompt, indeed,
can affect the
self-correction behavior.
But this is more about adjusting
the tendency for the model
to keep the initial response.
So in some cases
actually, this feedback,
after the feedback
prompt update,
there's no much regression
on the reasoning performance.
But then in this case,
this also doesn't
help the model to improve
over the initial performance.
So previously, we discussed
about this comparison
if we just do this
self-correction
over one initial response.
And we further compare
with another method
where basically we do
this self-correction
among multiple responses.
So for this, we compare with
the multi-agent debate baseline.
The idea is that we will
have the model generate
several responses
in parallel once.
Then we perform the
large language model
to reveal these
multiple responses
and give an updated one.
And for this
multi-agent debate, we
will compare with
self-consistency.
Recall that self-consistency
is just completely generated
solutions in parallel
and select the response
with the most
common final answer.
So in the previous
multi-agent debate papers,
they are showing
some improvement
over self-consistency.
But we find that
the major issue is
that they do not have a very
rigorous comparison in terms
of the token budget.
So actually, because in
the multi-agent debate,
each round for this specific
experiment has three responses.
But basically, if we keep
the same number of response
and budget, we will
see that actually still
self-consistency scales better
than the multi-agent debate.
Because at some point, again,
this multi-agent debate
performance stops improving.
But with more responses,
self-consistency performance
is still improving on this GSM8K
[? MATH ?] problem benchmark.
So given all this
discussion, then the question
here is how we can best
utilize the token budget
by integrating all these
different methods together.
So the fundamental question
is here, basically,
we need to understand how to
balance the inference budget
for generating multiple samples
in parallel or sequentially.
So actually, this is a
pretty difficult question
because it really depends
on the task and the model.
And in essence, it's about
whether the model for evaluation
is good at self-reflection
and correction
for your specific task.
So here, I'm showing an example
study from my colleagues
at Google, where
they are trying to--
basically, in this
specific experiments,
they are trying to
find the optimal way
to scale this token budget
to solve the math problems.
So actually here,
they trained a model,
which is supposed to be more
specialized at correcting
math solutions.
And also here, for the different
difficulty level of problems,
they study what's
the optimal ratio
to perform this
parallel generation
versus sequential generation.
So I would say this concrete
numbers will really vary
a lot among different models.
But basically here,
the overall conclusion
is that, for simple problems--
actually, the model can benefit
more from self-correction
because it knows
a more clear about
whether the current solution is
wrong and how it should revise.
But for harder problems,
actually, there
is a better point in the
middle about how much
you should perform
parallel generation.
And also, this
sequential refinement.
And then with this kind
of compute optimal factor
for different task
difficulty of problems,
they show that this compute
optimal curve can also
scale better than this
complete parallel generation.
And when we think about
inference time compute,
another factor we
should consider
is about the model size.
Because intuitively, with
the same FLOPs budget,
we can sample much more
solutions from a lighter model.
So more expensive model
does not perform much better
than a cheaper model, then it
will not be a very optimal way
to do the inference by calling
the more expensive model.
So basically, from
this empirical study
from the paper
inference scaling laws,
again, they will show that
with the optimal model
with different inference
budget can be a different.
Like when you have a smaller
inference time budget,
maybe you want to rely
more on the lighter models.
But basically, when
you have more budget,
probably you can utilize
the more expensive models,
which can probably give you
some boost on those very
challenging problems.
Where with the
smaller models, it
will be very hard to come up
with the final solution anyway.
So basically, in
this lecture, we
have covered different ways
to perform this inference time
scaling with the
more token budget.
So we talk about the
basic prompting techniques
about this search and
selection to increase
the width of exploring
the solution space.
And also, we talk about
iterative self-improvement.
And again, the best practice to
integrate with a large language
model should be adapted
according to its capabilities.
So you really need to consider
the underlying model capability
and also the task in your hand
to think about how you can best
combine all these
different techniques
and design a more efficient
and effective paradigm
for your task.
And finally, I also want to
talk about the general principle
of how to design effective
reasoning techniques.
And this actually will be
helpful for both inference time
techniques and training
time techniques.
So I guess many of you might
have heard about this The Bitter
Lesson from Richard Sutton.
But if not, I highly encourage
you to read this web page.
Actually, I will say this is
a very important guideline
for many of these modern
machine learning works.
And especially, with
the recent development
of large language models
and reasoning techniques.
So this article itself
has a lot of text.
But I will quote some most
interesting text in my opinion
here.
So basically, what
we really want
to develop as a
method is basically
[? those ?] that
continue to scale with
increased computation.
And when we want to
improve the AI agents,
we want to teach the model
to discover what we can,
not which contain what
we have discovered.
So it is more about
having some method
so that we can trigger
the model to know
how it can keep improving itself
and how to have the right way
to perform the reasoning.
So this is the end
of this lecture.
Thanks for listening.